<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Directions for the vvorthy receiuing of the Lords Supper with some few questions to the same purpose. By Robert Iension, Batchelor in Diuinity, and Minister of Gods Word, at New-Castle vpon Tine.</title>
            <author>Jenison, Robert, 1584?-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04377</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119429</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854636</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854636</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20065</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04377)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20065)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1313:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Directions for the vvorthy receiuing of the Lords Supper with some few questions to the same purpose. By Robert Iension, Batchelor in Diuinity, and Minister of Gods Word, at New-Castle vpon Tine.</title>
                  <author>Jenison, Robert, 1584?-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[54] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Purslowe] for Iohn Harrigat, and are to be sold at the Holy Lambe in Pater-noster Row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁴ (-D4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20065:1"/>
            <p>DIRECTIONS FOR THE WORTHY Receiuing of the Lords SVPPER: <hi>With ſome few Queſtions to</hi> the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>By ROBERT IENISON, Batchelor in Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and Miniſter of Gods Word, at <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> vpon <hi>Tine.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 11.28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Let a man examine himſelfe,</l> 
               <l>and ſo let him eate, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Iohn Harrigat,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Holy Lambe</hi> in <hi>Pater-noſter</hi> Row. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20065:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20065:2"/>
            <head>TO MY CHRISTIAN Hearers, of the Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of S. <hi>Nicholas</hi> and <hi>All-Saints,</hi> in <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> vpon <hi>Tine,</hi> eſpecially to the yonger and ruder ſort of them, R. I. <hi>wiſheth</hi> a competent meaſure of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Wiſedome and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, of the Spirit of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and of the feare of the Lord.</head>
            <p>WHat I now in heart, and euer in my hearty and dayly Prayers vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly <hi>wiſh</hi> on your behalfe, right
<pb facs="tcp:20065:3"/>
deare beloued Brethren, I am not (as you know) neither ſhall I euer, God aſsiſting, be awan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to further by my dayly and beſt endeuours for you, whether it bee by my Preaching, or by my Pen: (though this latter finds enough to doe, to prepare matter for your eares, not eyes.) To which end, as alſo for the publike good of many others, I haue not beene vnwilling at the requeſts of ſome, that theſe few directions following (which, nigh ſeuen yeeres ſince, were, at the earneſt intreaty of a neere friend, ſummed vp in haſte) ſhould, after they had alſo ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in your eares) ſee the light,
<pb facs="tcp:20065:3"/>
and paſſe, euen rudely, as at firſt, (when there was no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of publiſhing them) they were written, without any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, vnder the publike cenſure of the world; hoping, yea earneſtly deſiring, men would bring rather humble and hungring hearts, than curious and catching heads to the reading of them; that ſo they may indeed truely profite by them. As I ſhall vnderſtand theſe ruder, old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and haſtier Meditations are accepted of, I ſhall bee encouraged to greater, further, and freſher paines, in publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoone after, what, I hope,
<pb facs="tcp:20065:4"/>
will not bee vnprofitable to the Church of GOD, whoſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant I doe profeſſe my ſelfe, as alſo,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours, in the Lord,</hi> Robert Ieniſon.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Houſe, in</hi> New-Caſtle <hi>vpon</hi> Tine:
<date>Ian. 12. 1623.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20065:4"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian and carefull READER.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THou ſoule-ſicke Chriſtian, ſolace gather hence,</l>
               <l>Who art exil'd, in ſenſe, from Cana'ns Land,</l>
               <l>Lo, heer's a Briefe of that true Euidence,</l>
               <l>Which God hath pen'd with his moſt holy Hand;</l>
               <l>And leſt ſome doubt poſſeſſe thy ſilly Soule,</l>
               <l>That ſeale-leſſe Blancks thoſe Copies proue to bee,</l>
               <l>Take comfort; for th' inſpir'd, and ſacred Roule</l>
               <l>Of Gods great Booke, is ſealed vnto thee,</l>
               <l>With Graces rich inclos'd, both more and leſſe,</l>
               <l>If thou, to practiſe This, thy ſelfe addreſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ad eundem.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pacis Sacramenta licet ſignacula fiant,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non; niſi ſint ſacrâ mente recepta ſimul.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20065:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20065:5"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE DIRECTION FOR THE WORTHY RECEIVING OF THE Lords Supper.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <head type="sub">Three ſorts of dueties are to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of euery worthy Communicant: and three things eſpecially are to be looked vnto.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here muſt be an antecedent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in the receiuer, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> a performance of ſuch duties as may prepare him.</p>
               <p>There muſt bee a right behauiour in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the performance of this holy action.</p>
               <p>There are duties to be performed <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> after.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:20065:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of ſuch graces as are needfull in euery worthy Communicant.</head>
               <p>THis Sacrament, being a moſt holy ordinance of God, belongs not of right indifferently to all, but to ſuch one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as God doth accept and account as worthy in his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>We are all of vs in our ſelues, and by our corrupt nature, altogether vnworthy to partake of any mercy, and eſpecially of that grace which is both offered and ſealed vnto vs in the Sacrament.</p>
               <p>Yet God in his Sonne Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour is ready to accept vs, if we come clothed with the wedding garment of his righteouſneſſe, putting it on vs by faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith</hi> then of neceſſitie is required in euery worthy Communicant.</p>
               <p>Now true Faith, as it is grounded vpon ſound and ſauing <hi>Knowledge;</hi> ſo it is, and muſt be accompanied with true <hi>Repentance,</hi> and with the fruits thereof, eſpecially <hi>Charitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20065:6"/>Theſe foure graces then are neceſſary in euery worthy Communicant.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Knowledge.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Faith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Repentance.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Charitie.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Neither muſt we onely haue them, but we muſt <hi>know</hi> ſo much: which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is got by examination.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of Knowledge.</head>
               <p>GOd would haue vs offer vp to him <hi>reaſonable ſeruice</hi> as an acceptable ſacrifice, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. And not like ſhéep each follow other without knowledge and conſideration what we doe. <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> is the beginning of all grace, <hi>Prou.</hi> 19. 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. And Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance is highly diſpleaſing vnto God. In this Sacrament knowledge is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that we may examine our ſelues, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Rule</hi> of examination is <hi>partly</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> of God, by which we are to examine
<pb facs="tcp:20065:7"/>
our ſelues, our repentance, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and <hi>partly</hi> the Goſpell, by which we muſt examine our faith.</p>
               <p>Theſe two, as being the rules of our triall, muſt therefore firſt be knowne.</p>
               <p>We muſt then <hi>know</hi> (what the Law will tell vs) that howſoeuer we were made at the firſt, in our firſt parents, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam and Eue, in righteouſneſſe and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> according to Gods image, yet now we are all of vs by our firſt birth corrupt children, ouer-ſpred with the <hi>leproſie</hi> and leauen of <hi>ſinne,</hi> vnapt to conceiue or doe any thing truly good; prone and readie to doe all euill; and <hi>that accordingly</hi> we day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly bring forth and multiply the bitter fruits of <hi>Sinne</hi> by our actuall trangreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, not doing what good we ſhould doe, and doing the euill we ſhould not doe: and <hi>that</hi> therefore in this regard, we are all naturally as the ſlaues of Satan, who rules in our hearts by Sinne; ſo the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of death, and <hi>heires</hi> of damnation. The iuſt reward of our ſinne being the wrath and curſe of God, and death of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule euerlaſtingly.</p>
               <p>Yet we muſt further <hi>know</hi> (what the
<pb facs="tcp:20065:7"/>
                  <hi>Goſpell</hi> reueales, namely) that Gods will is not (ſuch is his loue) that we all ſhould periſh, (as we moſt iuſtly deſerue) but that we ſhould <hi>be ſaued, and come vnto the knowledge of the truth,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. That is, that all, of all ſorts belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Goſpell, ſhould be ſaued: the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſubſtance of the Goſpell being compriſed in theſe words, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16. <hi>God ſo loued the world, that he gaue his onely begotten Sonne, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting.</hi> For the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which promiſe to vs, wee muſt further <hi>know,</hi> that God hath annexed and added ſeales, which we call <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> whereof it is fit alſo, we ſhould haue ſome generall knowledge.</p>
               <p>Sacraments therefore <hi>are outward and viſible ſignes and ſeales of ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward inuiſible grace.</hi> Or, <hi>they are holy ſignes ordained of God, whereby the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of grace betweene God and the partie receiuing theſe ſignes, is ſolemne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſealed, confirmed, and ratified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This couenant of grace is that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> God <hi>on his part,</hi> Firſt, <hi>promiſeth</hi> to
<pb facs="tcp:20065:8"/>
be our God, that is, all in all vnto vs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. and that <hi>we ſhall not periſh,</hi> as we had deſerued, but <hi>haue euerlaſting life,</hi> through and by Chriſt Ieſus, which none of vs deſerues. But withall (as in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> couenants) he, ſecondly, <hi>requireth</hi> on our part, <hi>faith, Ioh.</hi> 3.16. with <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> and <hi>newneſſe of life,</hi> according to the tenour of the Goſpell, <hi>Repent and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, Mat.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.15. This being the couenant faire drawne, and largely <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <hi>written</hi> in the word of God, God, third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, annexeth his <hi>Seale</hi> hereunto, to ratifie what he hath promiſed, and to confirme and ſtrengthen our faith in his promiſe; as alſo he enioyneth vnto vs the vſe of the Sacraments, whereby we <hi>for our <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> parts,</hi> firſt, ſhewing our ſelues <hi>needfull</hi> of his mercies, both <hi>promiſe</hi> to to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what he requires: that is, to repent <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and beléeue: and alſo, by taking the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>binde our ſelues</hi> in ſeruice God, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that we will, forſaking all others, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the deuill, the world, and the fleſh (Gods and our maine enemies) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue his promiſes, depend on his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and ſerue him conſtantly to our
<pb facs="tcp:20065:8"/>
liues end, in all holy obedience.</p>
               <p>This is, firſt, done in <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> by which wee haue our admiſſion into the true Church of God ſealed vnto vs, and where firſt this couenant is confirmed and ſealed on both parts, Gods and ours.</p>
               <p>This ſame couenant is renued in the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> ſo often as we partake of it: for God thereby nouriſheth and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth vs in the true Church after our admiſſion into it by Baptiſme, confirms and ſeales vnto vs the ſame promiſe of the Goſpell, and requires like conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of faith and repentance from vs. And that we may better <hi>know the nature of this Sacrament,</hi> we muſt conſider that (each Sacrament being a ſigne) each thing, action, and circumſtance is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, to ſignifie and bring to our mind ſome other ſpirituall thing or action.</p>
               <p>As therefore in Baptiſme the water ſignifieth the bloud and ſpirit of Chriſt, whereby our ſinnes are waſhed and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; ſo in the Lords Supper;</p>
               <p n="1">1 The <hi>Bread</hi> and the <hi>Wine</hi> are now <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſet apart from the common vſe of fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our bodies, to repreſent and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb facs="tcp:20065:9"/>
vnto vs the body and blood of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, The Miniſter, <hi>ſetting theſe apart</hi> to this vſe, and conſecrating them; ſignifies, how God the Father, in his eternall Decree, hath ſet apart Chriſt our Sauiour, for the worke of our redemption, and conſecrated Him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, The <hi>breaking</hi> of the <hi>Bread,</hi> and <hi>powring</hi> out of the <hi>Wine,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the death of our Sauiour, whereby his Body was broken, and a ſeparation made, for a while, of the ſoule from the body, and the ſheading of His precious blood; by which he ſatisfied Gods wrath for beleeuers, and paid our debt, which was death.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> When the Miniſter <hi>offers and giues</hi> the Bread and Wine, we muſt conceiue, that God, to vs that beleeue, doth offer and giue (as hee promiſed in his Word) Chriſt his Sonne, with all the benefits of his death and Paſſion, which are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinne, reconciliation with God, and life eternall.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
                  <hi>Our receiuing</hi> of theſe from his hands, and feeding on them, ſignifie our Faith,
<pb facs="tcp:20065:9"/>
which is as the <hi>hand, mouth,</hi> and <hi>ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke</hi> of our ſoules, whereby wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Chriſt, and all theſe benefits now offered vnto vs; and feed on him ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, to life eternall: all which beeing done <hi>with others,</hi> put vs in mind of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <p>Now, all theſe we muſt well know &amp; vnderſtand, before we come to the Lords Table.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of Faith.</head>
               <p>BVt moreouer, it will not auaile vs onely <hi>to know</hi> theſe things, but wee muſt alſo bring Faith with vs, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the promiſe of the Goſpell: the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity whereof appeares from that which hath beene ſaid. The promiſe is made onely to them that beleeue, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16. Now this Sacrament is a ſeale of that promiſe, and of the Couenant of Grace: and therefore can ſeale vnto vs no more, nor no otherwiſe than is promiſed. Thee is nothing promiſed in the Word, to the vnfaithfull and vnbeleeuers, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:20065:10"/>
there is nothing ſealed to them in this Sacrament. Such then receiuing this Sacrament, receiue onely a Seale ſet to a blancke, or piece of white paper, wherein there is nothing written or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed: and ſuch men receiue the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to their hurt, and not to their good, becauſe they prophane the holy ordinance of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of Repentance.</head>
               <p>GOD, beſides our faith, doth alſo looke for our <hi>repentance,</hi> and new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life: For in this Sacrament we profeſſe our ſelues, to forſake our ſinnes and luſts, and the Deuill, and to become new men, and that wee will hereafter walke with God in new obedience: all our ſeruice and ſacrifices elſe will not be accepted of God: the Lord reiecteth all outward ſeruice and ceremonies (though they were ordained by himſelfe) when they are not accompanied with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of the heart, and innocency of life.
<pb facs="tcp:20065:10"/>
See <hi>Eſa,</hi> 1.13, 14, 15, 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 66.3. Therefore the Lord biddeth, when wee appeare before him, ſaying, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.16, 17. <hi>Waſh you, make you cleane, take away the euill of your wayes, ceaſe to do euill, learne to doe well, &amp;c</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.6. <hi>I will waſh mine hands in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, &amp; ſo I will compaſſe thine Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.</hi> This is eſpecially neceſſary in this Sacrament, wherein <hi>we ſhew forth the Lords death till he come.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. which we can doe no better, then by dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto ſinne our ſelues, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>mortification,</hi> which belongs to the firſt part of repentance; and muſt bee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with <hi>viuification,</hi> or newneſſe of life, which belongs to the ſecond part of repentance.</p>
               <p>The dueties then heere to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, are; Firſt, diligently and ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>examine</hi> our owne conſciences, and to find out our ſinnes, both originall and actuall; againſt both Law and Goſpell, that ſo we may returne to God by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.59. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.39, 40. Without this <hi>ſight</hi> of ſinne, wee cannot repent, as ſeeing nothing that hath tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:20065:11"/>
vs from God; and repenting, wee ſhall not be <hi>accepted,</hi> without this tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning firſt into our own hearts, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.1, 2. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.47. eſpecially we muſt labour to find out our <hi>ſpeciall ſinnes,</hi> vnto which we are moſt of all inclined, and which moſt of all wound our conſciences; to this end, we are carefully, Firſt, to obſerue the <hi>checks of conſcience;</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to obſerue our <hi>thoughts,</hi> on what eſpecially they runne moſt: Thirdly, to make vſe of ſome faithfull friend, who may faithfully tell vs, wherein they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vs to offend, ſeeing wee our ſelues are naturally blinded with ſelfe-loue: to this end, obſerue what ſinnes GODS Word preached or read condemnes: yea, obſerue (becauſe malice is quick-ſighted) what thine enemies obſerue in thee, and do caſt in thy teeth. But aboue all, fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, looke thy ſelfe and thy face, in the Glaſſe of Gods Law, and bring thy ſelfe to the Ballance and Touch-ſtone of Gods Word, both Law and Goſpell: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine thy ſelfe by each Article of thy Créede, and by each Commandement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, according to the true meaning of
<pb facs="tcp:20065:11"/>
each Commandement, which binds the inward man, and thine affections, as well as thy words and workes, and ſo thou maiſt find thy ſinne: (to this end) make vſe of that direction which is ſet downe in Maſter <hi>Perkins</hi> Booke of <hi>Repentance,</hi> and in the Booke called, the <hi>True Watch, firſt Part,</hi> and alſo <hi>the ſecond.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond duetie is, when wee ſee our ſin, <hi>to conſider how hatefull a thing it is in it ſelfe,</hi> how abominable to God &amp; all good men; that ſo wee may know it, with a féeling of the burthen of it, and with true ſorrow, that thereby wee ſhould offend, and ſhew our ſelues vnthankfull, to ſo louing a Father, and bountifull a GOD.</p>
               <p>Then muſt wee <hi>humble</hi> our ſelues in hearty and earneſt Prayer vnto GOD, <hi>confeſsing</hi> vnto him our ſinnes: our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne ſinnes generally, our knowne ſinnes particularly, and that fréely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any excuſe, defence, or hiding the leaſt of them. So did <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 32. &amp; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. and withall, wée muſt make earneſt intreaty, and deprecation to God, in the Name and mediation of Chriſt Ieſus,
<pb facs="tcp:20065:12"/>
who died for our ſinnes, that God would in mercy pardon them all, and ſeale vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the pardon of them by his Spirit: and héere euery one muſt frame his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion according to his owne néede, at the leaſt, in ſighes and ſobs of the heart, and the ſecret deſires thereof. To this end, (where &amp; whiles men cannot in priuate ſo well pray of themſelues) may bee vſed ſuch formes of prayer, as may bee found in the Leitargie of the Church and in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers godly Bookes, framed for this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular occaſion.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, there muſt be in our repentance, an holy and full <hi>purpoſe</hi> of heart, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment of new obedience for time to come, and a reſolution with Gods helpe to withſtand all ſinnes, and to vſe care to preuent all occaſions thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 6.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of Charity.</head>
               <p>BEſides all theſe, (which reſpect God) wee muſt alſo bee in loue and perfect charity with our neighboures; If they
<pb facs="tcp:20065:12"/>
haue offended vs, wee muſt bee ready to forgiue them, eſpecially vpon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt and acknowledgement, euen as God for Chriſts ſake forgaue vs, who had offended him, and as wée our ſelues in the Lords Prayer deſire to be forgiuen as wee our ſelues forgiue others.</p>
               <p>And if we haue iuſtly offended others, wee muſt ſeeke peace with them, &amp; their loue, and not be aſhamed to acknowledge our faults: This is ſo neceſſary, that God will haue <hi>his ſeruice</hi> ſtay till it bee performed, and without it will not accept <hi>our ſeruice</hi> and ſacrifice: He would haue vs leaue our offering; <hi>Goe thy way, and firſt bee reconciled to thy brother, &amp;c. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.24.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of Examination.</head>
               <p>ALl the fore-named things are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in euery Chriſtian at all times: but eſpecially when wee are to come to the holy Communion, wee are to practiſe theſe dueties, and to renew our faith and our repentance, &amp; to <hi>examine</hi> our ſelues,
<pb facs="tcp:20065:13"/>
whether theſe graces bee in vs in truth and ſynſerity, or no; according to 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. &amp; 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. eſpecially our <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our <hi>Faith</hi> is true, when, firſt, it is <hi>grounded</hi> namely on Gods Word, and not on traditions or authority of men: When wee find that Gods Word hath beene effectuall in vs and our ſelues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered thereby, ſo that we remaine not ſtill the ſame we were long ſince: and if ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we haue a loue and deſire to Gods Word, that by it our Faith may bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed.</p>
               <p>If our Faith be ſet on a right <hi>Obiect,</hi> that is, if it beleeue the ſame Word of God, as well the threatnings of it, as the promiſes: eſpecially, if it truely rely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mercy of GOD, and merits of CHRIST.</p>
               <p>By the <hi>fruites</hi> of it wee may know it, if our Faith <hi>purifie</hi> our heart, <hi>Act.</hi> 15 9. and if it work in vs an endeuour is pleaſe God in all things: if wee can beleeue God and his Trueth, euen before expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, as did the Woman of <hi>Canaan, Math.</hi> 15.22. and when wee feele not
<pb facs="tcp:20065:13"/>
his preſence; yea, if with <hi>Iob,</hi> wée can truſt in God though hee ſeeme to kill vs, and bee our enemie. Theſe may ſuffice for the preſent.</p>
               <p>Our repentance is then true, <hi>Firſt,</hi> when wee are ſorry, not ſo much for pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment or ſhame of our ſinne, as that thereby we haue offended and diſpleaſed our louing God and Father. <hi>Secondly,</hi> when we are ſorry and repent of all ſin, and doe not ſecretly deſire to liue in, or to inioy ſtill, any one pleaſant ſinne, but reſolue to leaue euery ſinne for the loue we owe to God. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> when wee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently and without delay, ſo ſoone as wée ſee and know our ſinne, doe repent: Sée <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.59, 60. <hi>I made haſte, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed not to keep thy Commandements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our <hi>Charity</hi> and loue to our brethren is then good and ſound, when wee loue them, not in by reſpects, for feare or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and delight, but as they are Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and <hi>becauſe God loues them,</hi> they being his friends; yea, becauſe we <hi>loue God:</hi> ſo, when wee wiſh them the beſt things, as that they were partakers with vs, of Chriſt, and of life euerlaſting:
<pb facs="tcp:20065:14"/>
when we can forget and forgiue priuate iniuries, and hate not their perſons, but their ſinnes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> If after examination wee finde theſe graces in vs, though but weake, yet wée may bée comforted, and wée muſt come: If we feele our ſelues vnworthy; <hi>knowe,</hi> that this ſenſe and feeling of ſin, (where there is no purpoſe to liue in ſin) is an argument of grace: by our corrupt nature, wee cannot diſcerne of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, but by grace onely. This Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is a remedy for our weaknes and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, Chriſt calling the weary, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and contrite vnto him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. Wée muſt not looke ſo much to come perfect, as to goe from it perfect, that is, more perfect and better then wée came. If thou canſt but deſire that grace which thou wanteſt, aſſure thy ſelfe of it, God will giue it; nay, He accepts the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire for the grace it ſelfe: For, if luſtfull deſire after a woman, be in Gods account adultery, and the ſinne it ſelfe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.28. much more is the deſire of any Grace, in Gods acceptance, the Grace it ſelfe deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: God inclining as much to mercy,
<pb facs="tcp:20065:14"/>
as to iuſtice, and as ready to take in good worth our good deſires, as to take the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of our euill deſires.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of dueties to be performed in this holy Action.</head>
               <p>OVr behauiour, during the time of the celebration of this holy Action, muſt be decent, with all reuerence to the high Maieſtie and preſence of God, and to his diuine Ordinance. Now, whereas the benefits and grace we receiue in this Sacrament, are conuayed vnto vs, as on <hi>Gods part, by His Spirit,</hi> ſo <hi>on our part,</hi> by a kind of reaſoning in the mind, and an inference and vſe-making from the colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or comparing &amp; conferring the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſignes with the things ſignified thereby: Wee are therefore, when wee come to the Table of the Lord, not to ſuffer our minds to wander after imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent matters, but to apply our hearts to diligent <hi>attention</hi> and <hi>conſideration,</hi> reaſoning with our ſelues, and making
<pb facs="tcp:20065:15"/>
vſe of euery thing in this Sacrament which we behold: as thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> When we behold and ſée bread and wine to be ſet apart, to ſignifie vnto vs the body and bloud of Chriſt, then muſt we further meditate and conſider:</p>
               <p>That this Sacrament is ordained for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> our ſpirituall nouriſhment, and increaſe in grace, thus differing from Baptiſme, which is the Sacrament of our firſt birth or regeneration: as bread therefore is for the ſuſtenance of man, and preſeruation of naturall life in him, ſo is Chriſts body and bloud ſpiritually, for the encreaſe and nouriſhing of our faith, and of Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in vs. For thus in decay of grace, we come to get aſſurance and féeling of it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Chriſt is therefore called the <hi>bread of life, Iohn</hi> 6.35.51. herein differing from common bread, that it onely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues life where life is once begun; but Chriſt begins life in vs, being ſet before vs in the preaching of the Goſpel, &amp; called the <hi>childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s bread, Mat.</hi> 15.26. And he is eaten by faith ſpiritually, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.56. He alſo continues and preſerues life in vs, as bread, eaten by the ſame faith, <hi>ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20065:15"/>Conſider, bread and wine are alſo for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> our <hi>comfort,</hi> and to make <hi>glad the heart of man, Pſalm.</hi> 104.14, 15. ſo alſo this Sacrament, and therefore in our fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and in our afflictions, we are to haue recourſe hither: this bread being like that meale which <hi>Eliſha</hi> caſt into the pot to make the pottage wholeſome, whereof it was ſaid before, <hi>death is in the pot,</hi> 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 4.40. <hi>and</hi> 41.</p>
               <p>When we ſée <hi>both bread and wine,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> conſider that Chriſt is our perfect Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Redéemer, both bread and water of life vnto vs, ſo that we néed not ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in whole or in part of any other.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Conſider hence alſo the <hi>neceſsitie</hi> of this Sacrament, eſpecially of the thing ſignified by this bread and wine: for as without bread and wine (or other moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture) we could not poſſibly liue (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we may well ſpare many vnneceſſary dainties) ſo, without this body and blood of Chriſt, and the merits thereon depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, it is impoſſible for any either to liue the life of grace here, or of glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <p>When we ſée the Miniſter ſet apart by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20065:16"/>
prayer and conſecration, theſe Elements from a common to an holy vſe, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies Gods eternall decrée in <hi>ſealing</hi> Chriſt to the worke of our redemption and ſaluation, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.27. Then further conſider and meditate on God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers excéeding great loue, <hi>Who ſo loued the world, that he gaue his only begotten Sonne Chriſt, to redeeme it, Ioh.</hi> 3.16. Which loue God ſetteth forth, ſéeing that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>(firſt) of himſelfe vnſought to, (Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> he the partie offended ſhould prouide <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> a Sauiour, and giue (thirdly) his onely <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> beloued Sonne for vs (Fourthly) before <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> we were, (Fifthly) whom he foreſaw to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> be vnable to helpe our ſelues, yea (Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) to be enemies vnto him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. Oh wonderfull loue of God! how did <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> loue God, when for his ſake he was ready to offer in ſacrifice his onely ſonne <hi>Iſaak?</hi> yet that was his duty, God ſo requiring it. How much more doth God loue vs, that fréely, yea contrary to our deſeruings, giues to death his onely Sonne Chriſt, one, ten thouſand times better then <hi>Iſaack?</hi> And thinke, if God ſo loued me, how ought I to loue him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine?
<pb facs="tcp:20065:16"/>
how ought I for his ſake to part with my deareſt and darling ſinnes? &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When we ſée the bread <hi>broken,</hi> and the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> wine <hi>powred</hi> out, then thinke on the death and paſſion of Chriſt, and on thoſe intolerable paines which he ſuffered both in body, and alſo much more in ſoule, not for himſelfe but for vs: and here alſo more ſpecially meditate: Firſt, on Chriſts ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall <hi>Loue</hi> to vs, who would ſo willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly become our ſuretie, and pay our debt to God, which is death, which we were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer able to haue endured: <hi>For greater loue then this hath no man, when any man beſtowes his life on his friends, Ioh.</hi> 15.13. But Chriſt is that <hi>good ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, who giueth his life for (vs) his ſheepe, Ioh.</hi> 10.11. How then (muſt I meditate) ſhould this inflame my heart with the loue of this my Sauiour? &amp;c. And how may I now reſt aſſured, that I ſhall be vndoubtedly ſaued? <hi>for if when I was a ſinner Chriſt died for me, much more then being now iuſtified by his blood, ſhal I be ſaued from wrath throgh him, &amp;c. Rom.</hi> 5.8.9.10.</p>
               <p>Secondly, conſidering his grieuous <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20065:17"/>
ſuffering and pangs for vs, his hands and his féet boared, his ſide pearced with a ſpeare, himſelfe mocked, and now ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining in ſoule the wrath of his Father due to our ſinnes; <hi>meditate,</hi> Didſt thou, ſwéet Sauiour, ſuffer ſuch torments for me, and ſhall not I endure an euill word for thée, and for the profeſſion of thy Name? Diddeſt thou on the Croſſe taſte Vineger and Gall for me; and ſhall I liue in pleaſure and delicacies, faring deliciouſly euery day, and ſo pleaſe my palate with exceſſe in delicious meates and wines? Diddeſt thou die for me; and ſhall not I die to ſinne, and thus ſhew forth in my ſelfe thy death? Yea, diddeſt thou die for me, and ſhall not I be ready to lay downe my life for thy Names ſake? &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, conſider alſo the cauſe of all this his ſuffering, which was not any ſinne of his, but our ſinne, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>and thinke and ſay,</hi> Lord when I looke vpon thée whom <hi>my ſinnes</hi> haue pierced, how ſhould I lament for thée? as one that mourneth for his onely Sonne, and bee ſorry for thée, as one is ſorry for his firſt
<pb facs="tcp:20065:17"/>
borne, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. Nay how ſhould I rather mourne for mine owne ſinnes, and hate them with a deadly hatred, whereby I crucifie thée againe, ſo louing a Sauiour: my ſinnes being the ſpeare that pierced thee, and the nailes that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened thée to the Croſſe? How weighty are my ſinnes, and how great the deſert thereof, which could not be borne by me, nor ſatisfied for by any thing I am able either to doe or ſuffer? but onely by thy precious death and bloud-ſhed of thée my deare Sauiour and my God bleſſed for euer. Shall I now henceforth account any ſinne light or little, which deſerued ſuch infinite puniſhment? Oh my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, poſſeſſe my heart with thy loue, teach mee to loue thee perfectly, and to hate all ſinne which coſt thee ſo deare, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When the Miniſter (repreſenting the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4:"/> perſon of God the Father) comes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thée to offer and giue to each the ſignes, this Bread and Wine; then firſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> meditate, and pray and ſay with the <hi>Centurion, Lord I am not worthy thou ſhouldeſt come vnder my roofe,</hi> and as <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſaid to <hi>Mary, whence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb facs="tcp:20065:18"/>
this to me, that</hi> (not the mother of the Lord, but) <hi>the Lord himſelfe ſhould come to me? Luk.</hi> 1.14. And with the bleſſed Virgin, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.38. <hi>Behold the ſeruant of the Lord, be it vnto thee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to thy word;</hi> and here ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, aſſure thy ſelfe of Gods eſpeciall loue to thée in particular, and take theſe ſignes as ſpeciall ſeales, and pledges of Gods ſpeciall loue towards thee; and here raiſe vp thy thoughts with this or the like meditation: Lord, whereas in thy Word thou offereſt Chriſt to all belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, though thou <hi>nameſt</hi> none, now I ſee thou meaneſt <hi>euen me,</hi> poore ſinner, as well as any: thou applieſt and aſſureſt <hi>vnto me</hi> thy generall promiſe, as if my name were recorded in thy Word, and written in that deede of gift, whereby thou giueſt and ſealeſt vnto all beleeuers eternall life; O Lord, now I may ſee, (and that without doubting) that indeed my name is written in the Lambs booke of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> When wee take and apply the Bread and Wine to our ſelues, then muſt wee <hi>ſtir vp our ſelues</hi> to take hold on Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:20065:18"/>
(<hi>Eſa.</hi> 64.7.) and be put in minde of the ſpeciall act of faith, which is, to apply and bring Chriſt home, to the inmoſt cloſet of our hearts, relying our ſelues, and putting our whole affiance, wholly and onely on him for ſaluation, ſtirring vp our faith, and by it féeding on our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour more and more; crying alſo, <hi>Lord, I beleeue, helpe my vnbeleefe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When we eat and drinke, then alſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> muſt we meditate, firſt, on our ſtrait <hi>vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> with Chriſt, whereby we become one with him, and he with vs, euen as the Bread and Wine turne to our nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and become one ſubſtance with vs, one fleſh and one bone; and what ſtraigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnion can there bee then this? Then rouze vp thy ſpirit &amp; ſay; <q>
                     <hi>O my bleſſed Sauiour,</hi> be thou vnto mee Bread and water of life for euermore: let this vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on once made by thy <hi>Spirit</hi> &amp; my <hi>faith,</hi> neuer again be diſſolued,</q> but faſten me vnto thée by the bond of my faith, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten and vnite thy ſelfe vnto me by the bond of thy Spirit, and that for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Let nothing diſſolue this knot, let not my ſinnes euer hereafter ſeparate
<pb facs="tcp:20065:19"/>
betweene thee and me <hi>Eſa.</hi> 59.2. But O Lord, let thy moſt precious, and pure, and holy body and blood, clenſe and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie my body and my ſoule, and either keepe them that they ſinne not againſt thee at any time preſumptuouſly, or if they ſinne, that by thy precious bloud they may be forthwith purged from ſin, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7. Yea O Lord, let me walke on in the ſtrength of this ſpirituall foode, this <hi>liuing</hi> Bread and Water of life, euen to eternall life, according to thy gracious promiſe and Word, whereby thou haſt ſaid; <hi>Whoſoeuer eateth my Fleſh and drinketh my Bloud hath eternall life, and if any man eat of this Bread, he ſhall liue for euer, Ioh.</hi> 6.51, 54. Let mee therefore hence be aſſured, <hi>that neither death nor life nor any thing elſe ſhall bee able to ſeperate me from this loue of thy Father, which is in thee his ſonne, my Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39. Heere alſo muſt we thinke of our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of all the benefits of Chriſt, both by <hi>imputation</hi> concerning our iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and alſo by <hi>infuſion</hi> concerning our ſanctification, ſeeing Chriſt neuer comes
<pb facs="tcp:20065:19"/>
alone: but as the married wiſe, though ſhe marry with the man himſelfe, and not with his lands or goods, yet being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of him, ſhe partakes of them too. Why then, O Lord, need I diſtruſt thy goodneſſe for any bleſſing, ſpirituall or temporall, ſeeing thou haſt giuen me thy Sonne Chriſt, and in him intereſt in all things, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22, 23. If thou ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redſt not thy Sonne, but gaueſt him for me to death, and now giueſt and applieſt him ſpiritually vnto me, how ſhalt thou not with him giue mee all things alſo? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. I will henceforth therefore neuer diſtruſt thy goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, when thou ſeeſt in this holy <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> action, others alſo rich and poore, of all ſorts without difference eat of the ſame Bread, and drinke of the fame Cup, bee put in minde of <hi>loue and charity to all:</hi> wee ſee where men familiarly conuerſe one with another, and liue together in one houſe, ſitting and feeding at the ſame table, there is mutuall loue, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and familiarity: elſe, it is very vnuſuall and vnnaturall: yea very beaſts by drawing together in the ſame Yoke,
<pb facs="tcp:20065:20"/>
grow familiar one with another, and ſhew loue in their kinde; what louing reſpect therefore owe I, euen to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of my fellowes and brethren, and to the leaſt of the Saints of God, ſeeing <hi>wee all that are many, are one bread and one body,</hi> becauſe we all are partakers of one Bread? 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17. and wee all haue beene made to drinke into one Spirit, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. Surely then becauſe I ſee there is one body (and but one) <hi>one Spirit, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme</hi> (yea one onely communion of Saints) <hi>one God and Father of all,</hi> I will therefore <hi>endeuour to keepe the vnity of the Spirit in the bond of peace, and with all humbleneſſe of minde, and meekneſſe with long ſuffering, ſupport others through loue,</hi> as the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts me, <hi>Epheſians</hi> 4.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. And becauſe I here ſee, my Sauiour makes no difference, and hath no reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſo they feare God, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.34, 35. but alike admits all to his Table, of all ſorts, rich and poore, noble and ignoble, &amp;c. and communicates himſelfe to all, I will henceforth deſpiſe none of GODS
<pb facs="tcp:20065:20"/>
Saints, not the leaſt member of Gods Church, whom God and Chriſt ſo loues, and hath done ſo much for, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.10. With theſe or ſuch like meditations ſhould our thoughts be taken vp, during the time of the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the bleſſed Sacrament, at which time eſpecially wee are to make conſcience of our thoughts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:20065:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. 9.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of duties to be performed after this action is ended.</head>
               <p>AS before we ſhould preſume to this Table, we muſt ſet our ſelues and our thoughts by meditations a part by times, ſome two or thrée daies, that we may come prepared (after the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Paſſeouer, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.3, 6.) So after this Sacrament is ſolemnly celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Church, each man and woman particularly, ſhould doe well to ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, ſome fit and conuenient time; to conſider well what is done, what God hath done for them, and what they haue promiſed, and ought to doe for God.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And here, <hi>Firſt,</hi> each one for himſelfe muſt in particular be <hi>thankfull</hi> for the high fauour vouchſafed him, that God would admit him to his Table, being in himſelfe vnworthy ſo much as to gather vp the crums that fall from it. (The forme of thanks may either be performed, as it ſhall pleaſe God by his Spirit to
<pb facs="tcp:20065:21"/>
helpe our infirmities, <hi>Rom</hi> 8.26. or helpe may be had from the order of the Church and from diuers good bookes of deuotion in this kinde.)</p>
               <p>Now to this end, each for himſelfe muſt well remember what he hath made promiſe and profeſſion of. Here we haue renued our promiſe and vow made in Baptiſme, to forſake the deuill, and haue taken the Sacrament vpon it, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as it were preſſe-money from God, to fight valiantly, conſtantly, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vnder his banner, againſt all his and our enemies, (after which, it is high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt his Maieſtie to reuolt or giue ouer) reſolue therefore now of conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to hold out to the end, whatſoeuer come of it, whatſoeuer oppoſition wée finde, from our traiterous and rebellious fleſh, from the ſcoffes of the world, from the aſſaults and ſlie ſuggeſtions of Satan. And as thou lookeſt that God ſhould make good, what he in his word hath promiſed, and in this Sacrament hath ſealed vnto thée, ſo looke that thou performe all thy vowes to God, elſe this Sacrament which thou haſt ſo often receiued, will be
<pb facs="tcp:20065:22"/>
a witneſſe againſt thée, and helpe to ſeale thy damnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> After all is performed, each muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine himſelfe what <hi>comfort,</hi> what <hi>ioy,</hi> what <hi>encreaſe</hi> of grace he hath reaped by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> this Sacrament. If we féele none, then muſt we either accuſe our ſelues, for want of ſufficient preparation before, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and then fly to God for pardon, &amp;c. Or if we haue in ſome meaſure endeuoured to examine and prepare our ſelues, then muſt we not be diſmayed, but truſt in the mercy of our good and gracious God for acceptation of our endeuours: Sée 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.18, 19. and depend on him for a bleſſing, ſéeing God hath not tyed his grace to the very time of receiuing: <hi>Light may be ſowne for the righteous, and ioy for the vpright in heart, as it is, Pſal.</hi> 97.11. and yet the harueſt of that comfort not reaped till afterwaad. So, the ſickman féeleth not for the preſent, the ſtrength and nouriſhment of the meate he hath taken, and yet is nouriſhed: the Word preached euen by our Sauiour, doth not alwayes take effect for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſee <hi>Act.</hi> 11.16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.16. And in
<pb facs="tcp:20065:22"/>
Baptiſme we receiue not the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſurance there made and ſealed vnto vs, till afterwards.</p>
               <p>If we haue felt any comfort, or God <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> more graciouſly preſent with vs in this Sacrament: Then, <hi>Firſt,</hi> let vs be more <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſpecially thankfull to him for it, not by our words, but by our déeds, by our liues and holy conuerſation, according to our purpoſes and promiſes here made and renued; and therefore,</p>
               <p>Firſt, pray with <hi>Dauid</hi> (after he and his people had offered willingly for the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Temple) <hi>Keepe this, O Lord, for euer, in the purpoſe and in the thoughts of the heart of thy people, and prepare their hearts vnto thee,</hi> 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.18. And <hi>then</hi> hauing fed on this heauenly food, ſhew forth the goodneſſe and ſtrength of this thy food receiued, by yéelding a plentifull fléece in new obedience, like the Shéepe which ſhewes (not by her bleating, but) by her fléece, how much, how well, how heartily ſhe hath eaten.</p>
               <p>Otherwiſe this were <hi>both</hi> for the ſhame of our Maſter Chriſt, at whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:20065:23"/>
table wee are ſo often and bountifully fed, if ſtill like <hi>Pharaohes</hi> ſeuen leane kine, wee remaine leane and ill fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 41.19, 20, 21. <hi>And alſo,</hi> doth argue ſome ſpirituall diſeaſe in vs, which like a conſumption hinders our growth and increaſe, or that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede for all the ſéeming comfort wee found, wee haue not truely receiued Chriſt, and haue him not abiding in vs, for hee hath ſayd, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.5. <hi>I am the Vine, ye are the Branches: hee that abideth in mee and I in him, the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſame bringeth forth much fruit.</hi> If wee haue feltt any comfort, then let vs hence bee moued, the oftner to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent this Table. As good men oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner frequent thoſe tables where their friends conſort.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> in caſe of temptation doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and vnbeléefe, flie hither for thy comfort, and for the conſſimation and ſtrengthning of thy faith: remember what thou haſt once and often recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: namely, ſignes and ſeales of the couenant of grace, as certaine tokens of Gods loue in Chriſt, and particular
<pb facs="tcp:20065:23"/>
aſſurances thereof: therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan off to Chriſt, ſhew him Gods gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall promiſe, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16. Sealed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee in particular, both in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme and in the Euchariſt, and let <hi>that</hi> be thy ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and comfort.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="question_and_answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:20065:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20065:24"/>
            <head>Some few Queſtions to the ſame purpoſe, with their Anſwers, grounded on <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. where it is ſaid, <hi>Abraham</hi> receiued the <hi>ſigne of Circumciſion, a ſeale of the righteouſneſſe of Faith, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Queſtion. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHat are Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Signes and ſeales of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of faith.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>What is the righteouſneſſe of faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt Ieſus, which he wrought by his obedience actiue and paſſiue, which is promiſed in the Goſpell,
<pb facs="tcp:20065:25"/>
and laid hold on, and receiued by faith, by which we become righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9, 10, 11. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 24.22, 23, 4.</p>
            <p>Qu. 3. <hi>Is this righteouſneſse ſignified and ſealed vnto vs in the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is in as much as Chriſt and all the benefits of his death, as pardon of ſinne; or vnion with him, and communion one with another, as alſo our communicating in all theſe benefits, are thereby ſignified and ſealed to beleeuers, and to them onely.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>How is this Sacrament a Signe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In as much as it and all the elements and actions vſed in it, are ordained of God, to ſignifie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent vnto the faithfull, what God hath done and doth for vs in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>What is required of each Communicant in this regard?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20065:25"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is required that at, and neere about the time of communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, he, comming prepared by <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>repentance,</hi> and hauing a right <hi>knowledge</hi> of the meaning and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of each thing and action, doe accordingly make vſe thereof, by a further holy meditation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 6. <hi>What meditation is affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the bare elements of Bread and Wine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe being appointed as ſignes to ſignifie the body and bloud of Chriſt, we ſo conceiuing of them, muſt hence further be put in minde; Firſt, of the <hi>nature</hi> of this Sacrament <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that it is not to beginne grace in vs, but for our ſpirituall nouriſhment &amp; growth in grace, as alſo comfort, as Bread and Wine doe not giue life where it is not (as not to a dead man, or to an image) but where it is, though in a languiſhing manner. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> when we ſee both Bread and
<pb facs="tcp:20065:26"/>
Wine, we muſt conſider that Chriſt is to vs perfect nouriſhment, and a perfect Sauiour, both a perfect <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Prieſt</hi> and <hi>King.</hi> Thirdly, we muſt hence thinke of the neceſſity of Chriſt ſignified by Bread and Wine, being as neceſſary, in regard of our ſpirituall life, as bread and drinke are to our naturall life.</p>
            <p>Qu. 7. <hi>What are you to meditate on, when you ſee the Miniſter, by Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and by Prayer, ſet apart theſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from their common vſe, to an holy vſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This, ſignifying that God the Father in his eternall decree did ſet apart, and ſeale Chriſt Ieſus his Sonne in due time to finiſh the work of our redemption, calls on me to conſider his <hi>infinite loue</hi> to mankind, and to mee in particular, in not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his onely Sonne for my ſake, and muſt alſo teach me to loue him againe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20065:26"/>Qu. 8. <hi>What muſt you meditate on, when you ſee the Bread broken, and the Wine powred out?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Seeing hereby is ſignified the painefull and bloudy death of Chriſt for me, this muſt teach me to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> conſider, firſt, the infinite loue of Chriſt, who would thus die for me,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to redeeme me from death; ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the cauſe hereof, not his, but mine owne ſinnes, which therefore I am not to account light of; thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> what duty I hence owe to him, how that I ought to loue him againe, and not refuſe to ſuffer any thing for him according to his Will.</p>
            <p>Qu. 9. <hi>What meditation is affoorded from the Miniſters comming towards vs, his offering and giuing thoſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to each of vs in particular?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This (ſignifying that God doth offer and giue in particular to euery one of vs Chriſt, and all the benefits of his death, which hee offered to all
<pb facs="tcp:20065:27"/>
generally in the Word preached) giues vs to conſider, that God would haue vs euery one to be particularly aſſured of his loue and good will in Chriſt Ieſus, (neither out of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of our vnworthineſſe, excluding our ſelues from his mercy, nor for want of ſpeciall application, loſing the benefits of Chriſt) and in the conſideration of this mercy, from the heart, to acknowledge with the <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Lord, I am not worthy thou ſhouldeſt come vnder my roofe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 10. <hi>When thou takeſt and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeſt to thy ſelfe this bread and wine, what muſt this put thee in minde of?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It, ſignifying my <hi>faith,</hi> which is as the <hi>hand, mouth,</hi> and <hi>ſtomacke</hi> of my ſoule, muſt put me in mind, that as God will haue euery man haue faith for himſelfe (without which Chriſt profiteth no man of age:) ſo, to renue the act of my faith, and at this time to ſtirre vp my ſelfe to take
<pb facs="tcp:20065:27"/>
hold on Chriſt, and to leane and reſt my ſelfe on my <hi>Beloued,</hi> aſſuring my ſelfe by this my renued act of faith, that Chriſt and all his benefits are as certainly mine, as that the bread is now truely receiued into my hand, and is become mine.</p>
            <p>Q. 11. <hi>When thou eateſt and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Bread and Wine, which turne into the ſubſtance of our bodies, what muſt here be thought on?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This ſignifying not onely and ſimply our faith (<hi>Iohn</hi> 6.35) by which we daily feed vpon Chriſt in the Word ſpiritually, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.53, 54, 55, 63. but our <hi>Vnion</hi> by faith, and neerer coniunction with Chriſt, muſt accordingly put vs in minde, and alſo aſſure vs of our vnion with him; and that as truly as the Bread and Wine we eat and drinke, are turned into our ſubſtance, to repaire ſtrength decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo aſſuredly are we changed, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milated and made conformable vnto
<pb facs="tcp:20065:28"/>
Chriſt (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10.) and incorporated into him, and ſo fed, refreſhed, and inwardly ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his Body and Bloud.</p>
            <p>Qu. 12. <hi>But are Sacraments alſo ſeales, and particularly this of the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> They are, and that both on Gods behalfe, to aſſure the beleeuer that Gods promiſes, and all theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Chriſt do moſt certainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto him; <hi>and on our part,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we, by taking and receiuing theſe ſignes, bind our ſelues a new to keepe our couenant with God, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all thoſe promiſes of ours (as of new obedience and mortification) which wee by our ſureties made to him in Baptiſme.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20065:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
